Guide to the National Education Association-Committees records, 1857-1996 NEA1003.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association Records-Committees
1857-1996
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
National Education Association of the United States
NEA1003.RG
141 Linear Feet
Biographical/Historical note
The National Education Association (NEA) is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. In 2010, the NEA had 3.2 million members and is located in Washington, D.C. The group holds a congressional charter under Title 36 of the United States Code granted in 1906.
The NEA describes itself as a professional employee organization. The mission of the National Education Association is "to advocate for education professionals and to unite our members and the nation to fulfill the promise of public education to prepare every student to succeed in a diverse and interdependent world."
The NEA is a volunteer-based organization that relies upon its members to perform much of the Association's work. The members are supported by staff at the local, state, and national levels with the stated goal of "building great public schools for every student."
In 1857, Thomas W. Valentine, president of the New York State Teachers Association, issued a nation-wide invitation to teachers to unite in Philadelphia behind a common voice for America's growing public school system. After the meeting, the National Teachers Association (NTA) was formed with a membership of about 100. Minority educators were allowed to join at the start, but women were not allowed to join until 1866.
In 1870, the NTA merged with the American Normal School Association, the National Association of School Superintendents, and the Central College Association renaming itself the National Education Association. For the first 100 years of its existence, the NEA was controlled by administrators, and worked to further the interests of the "education profession" as a whole.
In the 1960's, after the first passage of a collective bargaining law for public employees, the NEA adopted union activities in addition to its operations as a professional association.
The NEA merged with the American Teachers Association (ATA), formerly the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS) in 1966.
In 1998, a proposed merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) failed when it was rejected by NEA's Representative Assembly. Several NEA state affiliates have merged with their AFT counterparts, effectively forming a single association.
Over the years, the NEA has been a leader in national education reform and improvement movements. It has worked to improve the education provided to American school children through lobbying and campaigning on the local and national level as well as by promoting strong teacher education programs and continuous professional assessment and development.The National Education Association (NEA) is the largest professional organization and largest labor union in the United States, representing public school teachers and other support personnel, faculty and staffers at colleges and universities, retired educators, and college students preparing to become teachers. In 2010, the NEA had 3.2 million members and is located in Washington, D.C. The group holds a congressional charter under Title 36 of the United States Code granted in 1906.
The NEA describes itself as a professional employee organization. The mission of the National Education Association is "to advocate for education professionals and to unite our members and the nation to fulfill the promise of public education to prepare every student to succeed in a diverse and interdependent world."
The NEA is a volunteer-based organization that relies upon its members to perform much of the Association's work. The members are supported by staff at the local, state, and national levels with the stated goal of "building great public schools for every student."
In 1857, Thomas W. Valentine, president of the New York State Teachers Association, issued a nation-wide invitation to teachers to unite in Philadelphia behind a common voice for America's growing public school system. After the meeting, the National Teachers Association (NTA) was formed with a membership of about 100. Minority educators were allowed to join at the start, but women were not allowed to join until 1866.
In 1870, the NTA merged with the American Normal School Association, the National Association of School Superintendents, and the Central College Association renaming itself the National Education Association. For the first 100 years of its existence, the NEA was controlled by administrators, and worked to further the interests of the "education profession" as a whole.
In the 1960's, after the first passage of a collective bargaining law for public employees, the NEA adopted union activities in addition to its operations as a professional association.
The NEA merged with the American Teachers Association (ATA), formerly the National Association of Teachers in Colored Schools (NATCS) in 1966.
In 1998, a proposed merger with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) failed when it was rejected by NEA's Representative Assembly. Several NEA state affiliates have merged with their AFT counterparts, effectively forming a single association.
Over the years, the NEA has been a leader in national education reform and improvement movements. It has worked to improve the education provided to American school children through lobbying and campaigning on the local and national level as well as by promoting strong teacher education programs and continuous professional assessment and development.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the committees of the NEA. The collection contains twenty-six series reflecting the bodies and their records. The twenty-six series are: the Citizenship Committee, Committee of Constitutional Compliance, Committee on Educational Finance, Committee on International Relations, Compliance Committee, Committee on Planning and Organizational Development, Committee on Professional Ethics, Committee on Tenure and Academic Freedom, Committee on Women's Concerns, Committee Reports, Copyright Committee, Joint Committee of the NEA and American Legion, Joint Committee of the NEA and American Library Association, Joint Committee of the NEA and American Medical Association, Joint Committee of the NEA and American Teachers Association, Joint Committee of the NEA and Magazine Publishers Association, Joint Committee of the NEA and National Congress of Parents and Teachers, Joint Committee of the NEA and National School Board Association, Legislation Committee, Resolutions Committee, Special Services Committee, Standing Committee on Benefits, Standing Committee on National Public Relations, Streamlining Committee, Committee on Credit Unions, and Joint Committee of the NEA and Association of American Publishers.
Arrangement note
The collection is organized into roughly alphabetical series based upon the NEA's organization. Records have been allocated largely to their offices of origin and reflect the work done within the offices, departments, divisions and units. Due to the immense size of the collection and the constraints placed upon the finding aid by the archival management system utilized by George Washington University, the collection was further divided up into parts.
Organized into 26 Series. Citizenship Committee; Committee on Constitutional Compliance; Committee on Educational Finance; Committee on International Relations; Committe on Planning and Organizational Development; Committee on Professional Ethics; Committee on Tenure and Academic Freedom; Committee on Women's Concerns; Committee Reports; Compliance Committee; Copyright Committee; Joint Committee of the NEA and the American Legion; Joint Committee of the NEA and American Library Association; Joint Committee and American Medical Association; Joint Committee of the NEA and American Teachers Association; Joint Committee of the NEA and Magazine Publishers Association; Joint Committee of the NEA and National Congress of Parents and Teachers; Joint Committee of the NEA and National School Board Association; Legislation Committee; Resolution Committee; Special Services Committee; Standing Committee on Benefits; Standing Committee on National Public Relations; Streamlining Committee; Committee on Credit Unions; Joint Committee of the NEA and Association American Publishers.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Some files are restricted. Those files flagged as restricted are subject to review by Special Collections staff before being made available for research. As researchers request materials, a review of the documents will take place. Staff will remove any documents with social security numbers, employee numbers or other sensitive identifying information. Any document found including this information is closed for 90 years from date of creation, or until verifiable proof of a person's death is given. After these documents are removed the folder will be available for research. In some cases, items may be photocopied and redacted. The redacted copy will then be placed in the publicly available folder. All other materials in a folder will be freely available for immediate use and will be marked as having been reviewed by Special Collections staff. After folders have been reviewed using these procedures and the confidential materials have been removed, the restriction shall be lifted.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Education -- United States -- History; Teachers; Labor unions; Professional Employees; Professional Associations; Educational law and legislation; Teachers' assistants; Education -- Finance
- Citizenship Committee, 1940-1972; Series 1; 26 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Series contains materials created within the Citizenship Committee. The files include agenda books from meetings, conference papers, form letter books, reports and publications, Lucille Ellison's papers and conference planning papers of the National Conference on Citizenship.
  These files cover many interesting issues involving the national identity around WWII and how to include patriotism and American civics into the classroom. The National Conference on Citizenship papers illustrate the strong partnership between the U.S. Department of Justice and the NEA in encouraging American studies in the classroom. This subseries provides great source material for studying the intersection of American Patriotism, Civics and education during the 1940s-1950s.
  Biographical/Historical note
  The Citizenship Committee was one of the first committees created by the NEA in 1935. Its initial purpose was to study the requirements for schools in preparing students to be active citizens. Later the committee was involved with introducing voting rights and lowering the voting age to 18.
  The committee also co-sponsored an annual conference with the Department of Justice called the National Conference on Citizenship. The committee also encouraged teachers to pursue political causes and to hold office.
  From 1963-1970, the committee held regional political clinics throughout the U.S. In 1969, the committee recommended that a national political action committee be formed, but it was initially turned down. In 1970, it was reconsidered, and eventually created in 1972. This sealed the end of the committee.
  "The National Education Association: The Power Base for Education" by Allan M. West, 1980.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by title, and chronologically within the same title.
  - Agenda Books, May 1947; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, December 1947; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, February 1948; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, July 1948; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, October 1948; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, December 1948; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, February 1949; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, May 1949; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, July 1949; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 9)
  - Agenda Books, September 1949; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 10)
  - Agenda Books, December 1949; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 11)
  - Agenda Books, March 1950; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 12)
  - Agenda Books, July 1950; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 13)
  - Agenda Books, November 1950; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 14)
  - Agenda Books, October 1951; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 15)
  - Agenda Books, January 1952; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 16)
  - Agenda Books, March 1952; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 17)
  - Agenda Books, May 1952; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 18)
  - Agenda Books, September 1952; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 19)
  - Agenda Books, January 1953; Series 1 (Box 1113, Folder 20)
  - Agenda Books, June 1953; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, September 1953; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, December 1953; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, March 1954; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, June 1954; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, September 1954; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, December 1954; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, April 1955; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, September 1955; Series 1 (Box 1114, Folder 9)
  - Agenda Books, December 1955; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, April 1956; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, September 1956; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, November 1956; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], May 1957; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], May 1957; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, September 1957; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, January 1958; Series 1 (Box 1115, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, April 1958; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, September 1958; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, December 1958; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, April 1959; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, September 1959; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, December 1959; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, April 1960; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, September 1960; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, December 1960; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 9)
  - Agenda Books, April 1961; Series 1 (Box 1116, Folder 10)
  - Agenda Books, September 1961; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, February 1962; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, April 1962; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, September 1962; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, January 1963; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, April 1963; Series 1 (Box 1117, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, July 1963; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, October 8, 1966; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, January 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, February 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, April 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, July 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, August 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, December 1967; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, February 1968; Series 1 (Box 1118, Folder 9)
  - Agenda Books, June 1968; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, September 1968; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, January 1969; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, February 1969; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, March 1969; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, June 1969; Series 1 (Box 1119, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, September 1969; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books, January 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books, February 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, March 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, May 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, June 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, October 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, December 1970; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], February 1971; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 9)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], February 1971; Series 1 (Box 1120, Folder 10)
  - Agenda Books, March 13, 1971; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 1)
  - Agenda Books [file 1/2], May 1971; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 2)
  - Agenda Books [file 2/2], May 1971; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 3)
  - Agenda Books, June 1971; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 4)
  - Agenda Books, November 1971; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 5)
  - Agenda Books, January 1972; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 6)
  - Agenda Books, March 1972; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 7)
  - Agenda Books, May 1972; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 8)
  - Agenda Books, June 1972; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 9)
  - Budget, 1966-1967; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 10)
  - Budget and Accounts, 1959-1960; Series 1 (Box 1121, Folder 11)
  - Carr, Elizabeth, 1967; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 1)
    Carr, Elizabeth
  - Case Files-Gainer, Earl J., 1964-1970; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 2)
    Gainer, Earl J.
  - Case Files-Grecco Bill, 1966-1968; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 3)
  - Case Files-Lay, Elery A., 1969-1970; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 4)
    Lay, Elery A.
  - Case Files-Right of a Teacher to Hold Office [file 1/3], 1968-1972; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 5)
  - Case Files-Right of a Teacher to Hold Office [file 2/3], 1968-1972; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 6)
  - Case Files-Right of a Teacher to Hold Office [file 3/3], 1968-1972; Series 1 (Box 1122, Folder 7)
  - Centennial Celebration (Press Releases) [file 1/2], 1957; Series 1 (Box 1123, Folder 1)
  - Centennial Celebration (Press Releases) [file 2/2], 1957; Series 1 (Box 1123, Folder 2)
  - Citizenship News and Ideas, April 1953 - January 1953; series 1 (Box 4312, Folder 22)
  - Conference Papers (First and Second), 1946-1947; Series 1 (Box 1123, Folder 3)
  - Conference Papers (Third) [file 1/2], 1947; Series 1 (Box 1123, Folder 4)
  - Conference Papers (Third) [file 2/2], 1947; Series 1 (Box 1124, Folder 1)
  - Conference Papers (Fourth) [file 1/2], 1949; Series 1 (Box 1124, Folder 2)
  - Conference Papers (Fourth) [file 2/2], 1949; Series 1 (Box 1124, Folder 3)
  - Conference Papers (Fifth) [file 1/2], 1950; Series 1 (Box 1124, Folder 4)
  - Conference Papers (Fifth) [file 2/2], 1950; Series 1 (Box 1125, Folder 1)
  - Conference Papers (Fifth) [file 1/2], 1950; Series 1 (Box 1125, Folder 2)
  - Conference Papers (Fifth) [file 2/2], 1950; Series 1 (Box 1125, Folder 3)
  - Conference Papers (Sixth), 1951; Series 1 (Box 1125, Folder 4)
  - Conference Papers (Sixth-Correspondence) [file 1/2], 1951; Series 1 (Box 1125, Folder 5)
  - Conference Papers (Sixth-Correspondence) [file 2/2], 1951; Series 1 (Box 1126, Folder 1)
  - Conference Papers (Sixth-Publicity Book) [file 1/2], 1951; Series 1 (Box 1126, Folder 2)
  - Conference Papers (Sixth-Publicity Book) [file 2/2], 1951; Series 1 (Box 1126, Folder 3)
  - Conference Papers (Seventh-Publicity Book) [file 1/2], 1952; Series 1 (Box 1126, Folder 4)
  - Conference Papers (Seventh-Publicity Book) [file 2/2], 1952; Series 1 (Box 1126, Folder 5)
  - Conference Papers (Eighth-Correspondence) [file 1/2], 1953; Series 1 (Box 1127, Folder 1)
  - Conference Papers (Eighth-Correspondence) [file 2/2], 1953; Series 1 (Box 1127, Folder 2)
  - Conference Papers (Eighth-Organization of Conference Papers), 1953; Series 1 (Box 1127, Folder 3)
  - Conference Papers (Eighth-Publicity Book) [file 1/2], 1953; Series 1 (Box 1127, Folder 4)
  - Conference Papers (Eighth-Publicity Book) [file 2/2], 1953; Series 1 (Box 1127, Folder 5)
  - Conference Reports (First), 1946; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 1)
  - Conference Reports (Second), 1947; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 2)
  - Conference Reports (Third), 1948; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 3)
  - Conference Reports (Fourth), 1949; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 4)
  - Conference Reports (Fifth), 1950; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 5)
  - Conference Reports (Sixth), 1951; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 6)
  - Conference Reports (Seventh), 1952; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 7)
  - Conference Reports (Eighth), 1953; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 8)
  - Conference Reports (Ninth), 1954; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 9)
  - Conflict of Interest Policy, 1967-1970; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence [file 1/2], 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence [file 2/2], 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 1128, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence-Citizenship Committee, 1965-1969; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-Evans, Evan, 1950; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 2)
    Evans, Evan
  - Correspondence-Fischer, George, 1969-1971; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 3)
    Fischer, George D.
  - Correspondence-Garcia, Fred, 1968-1971; Series 1; Garcia, Fred (Box 1129, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Lees, Bob, 1964-1969; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 5)
    Contains 7 photos and 3 negatives.
    Lees, Bob
  - Correspondence-Mitchell, Robert F., 1970-1971; Series 1; Mitchell, Robert F. (Box 1129, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence-Newport, RI Case, 1959; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence-Personnel Policy on Political Activity, 1955-1970; Series 1 (Box 1129, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-Presentations-AASA Meeting, 1969; Series 1 (Box 1130, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-Prospective Personnel Policies, 1971-1972; Series 1 (Box 1130, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence-Robb, Felix C. [file 1/2], 1966-1969; Series 1; Robb, Felix C. (Box 1130, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence-Robb, Felix C. [file 2/2], 1966-1969; Series 1; Robb, Felix C. (Box 1130, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence-Robinson, Thomas E., 1966-1968; Series 1; Robinson, Thomas E. (Box 1130, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence-Scrolls, Tributes and Awards, 1964-1967; Series 1 (Box 1130, Folder 6)
    Contains 16 photos and 5 negatives.
  - Correspondence-Shepoiser, Lawerence, 1963-1968; Series 1; Shepoiser, Lawerence (Box 1130, Folder 7)
    Contains 1 photo.
  - Correspondence-Star Spangled Banner, 1967-1970; Series 1 (Box 1130, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence-Summary Reports, 1946-1965; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence-Turner, Annie Mae, 1965-1969; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 2)
    Turner, Annie Mae
  - Correspondence-The White House, 1966-1969; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 3)
  - District of Columbia...Puzzle in Politics and Some Suggestions for Action Towards a Solution, 1966; series 1 (Box 4312, Folder 23)
  - Early Conference Materials, 1948-1953; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 4)
  - Every Citizen Holds Office, January 1964; series 1 (Box 4312, Folder 24)
  - "Every Citizen Holds Office" Thank You Letters, 1964; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 5)
  - Filmstrip-"We Hold These Rights"-Showing Form, circa 1970; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 6)
  - "For Citizenship Recognition Day" Leaflet Catalog, Ca. 1941; Series 1 (Box 4040, Folder 2)
  - Form Letter Book, 1954; Series 1 (Box 1131, Folder 7)
  - Form Letter Book, 1955; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 1)
  - Form Letter Book, 1956; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 2)
  - Form Letter Book, June 1956-October 1958; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 3)
  - Form Letter Book, 1957; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 4)
  - Form Letter Book, January 1959-December 1960; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 5)
  - Form Letter Book, January 1961-November 1961; Series 1 (Box 1132, Folder 6)